Vincenzo Russo

7 Summerlands Avenue • W3 6EN London • United Kingdom

Mobile: +44 75 178 90 210 (UK) / +39 320 094 07 27 (Italy) • E-Mail: vincenzo.russo@neminis.org

Homepage: http://neminis.org • Skype: enzoru • Gender: Male • D.O.B.: 6th of February 1982



Introduction

I am a **computer scientist and engineer**, as well as a passionate, detail-obsessed, **senior developer** and **technical leader** with strong knowledge of **OOP**, **AOP**, **Design Patterns**. With a variegate experience, from research in **Data Mining** and **AI**, to hands-on **Web** enterprise development, I believe I can add strong value to highly qualified teams working on Web and Data technologies. I enthusiastically believe in scientific research, knowledge sharing, and open source development.

Areas of interest and competence

Main: Web, Software Engineering, Data Mining, Information Retrieval, Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing - Others: Operating Systems, Optimisation Problems

Work experiences

Software Architect – The Economist Newspaper Ltd., London, UK

14 Jun 2010 - Present

Senior member of the team that brought the online publishing platform of the whole *economist.com* from <u>Cold Fusion/Oracle</u> to <u>Drupal</u> (<u>Pressflow</u>). Migration was accomplished along with functional and architectural critical improvements. Fully Agile <u>Scrum</u>-driven project; mission-critical, performance and scalability critical, etc.

CMS Practice Manager – Ibuildings UK Ltd., London, UK Technical Lead Engineer – Ibuildings UK Ltd., London, UK Senior Software Engineer – Ibuildings UK Ltd., London, UK

01 Jan 2010 - 01 Jun 2010 01 Dec 2009 - 01 Jun 2010 03 Nov 2008 - 30 Nov 2009

Ibuildings is a PHP authority in the UK, The Netherlands and Italy, focused on mission-critical, large scale web applications, with state-of-the-art technologies. As <u>Senior Software Engineer</u>, I focused on the complete application life-cycle via Continuous Integrations systems, Deployment tools, etc. As <u>Tech Lead Engineer I</u> was also responsible for the functional and technical specifications, web effort estimation, planning and designing, leading and coaching team members, preventing critical issues. As <u>CMS Practice Manager</u>, I organised and managed everything revolved around CMSs (*learning material, coding standards, continuous integration and multi-stage deployment solutions, developers coaching, application architecting, etc.*), with a primary focus on Drupal, the preferred CMS for most applications.

Clients I worked for: Ladbrokes (custom PHP dev and Zend Framework), Channel Five (Drupal), Turner Broadcasting System (Pressflow Drupal), Haymarket Media Group (Pressflow Drupal).

Technical Manager – Pulse S.a.s, Naples, IT

01 Jan 2007 – Dec 2008

Pulse was a small and fresh company focused on the state-of-the-art of the web technologies, mixing them with expertise in other areas (such as HCI, Data Mining, Mobile technologies), to obtain outstanding results for their clients. Pulse also carries on some internal research projects for Web RAD and Enterprise CMS. *Focus*: OO-PHP, PHP Frameworks, PHP CMSs (Drupal), MySQL, Web Services, Unit Testing, Java Enterprise, Design Patterns, Data Mining (Xapian, Vogoo, Lucene, etc.), etc.

Senior Developer - Incsub LLC, Melbourne, AU

Oct 2008 - Oct 2008

Incsub is a consultancy and development company that provide custom websites built around WordPress MultiUser (WPMU). Focus: OO-PHP, WordPress Mu, MySQL, etc. Roles: Software Engineer and Developer.

Machine Learning Researcher – University "Federico II", Naples, IT

01 May 2008 – 31 Oct 2008

University "Federico II" of Naples is one of the most important italian university. SoLCo is an applied research project that aims at bringing state-of-the-art information retrieval instruments to companies and public offices into the local government. *Roles:* Machine learning researcher (clustering and classification of textual documents) and C++ developer.

Data Mining Researcher and Engineer – University "Federico II", Naples, IT

15 Feb 2008 – 30 Sep 2008

DAME (http://voneural.na.infn.it – formerly VONeural) is an applied research project that aims at developing a comprehensive state-of-the-art C++ framework for astrophysics data mining. *Roles*: <u>Data mining researcher</u>, <u>software engineer</u> and <u>C++ developer</u>.



Software Engineer and DB Architect – CINI ITeM Labs, Naples, IT

07 Feb 2006 - 31 Mar 2007

CINI is the Italian Inter-university Consortium for Informatics. At ITeM Labs I was a <u>Software Engineer</u>, mainly focused on the Italian website and e-learning systems for the EUCIP¹ certification. *Focus*: <u>PHP</u>, <u>Drupal</u>, <u>MySQL</u>, <u>SOAP</u>, <u>Dokeos LMS</u>, <u>Linux systems</u>.

Software Engineer and DB Architect – EFAEP, Brussels, BE / AISA, Milan, IT 2004 – 2005

EFAEP is an Association of Environmental Experts from all over Europe and AISA is one of the italian environmental association. I was in the ENEP² (formerly DBEP) team that created a CMS from scratch to manage a database of environmental professionals' curricula. *Roles*: <u>Software Engineer</u>, <u>DB engineer and administrator</u> (PostgreSQL), PHP, SQL and PL/pgSQL developer, <u>Linux system administrator</u>.

Web Software Engineer and LAMP developer freelance, Self-employed 2000 – 2005

Delphi developer freelance, Self-employed 1999 – 2000

Education and Training

Master Degree in Computer Science³

2000 - 2007

I graduated **cum laude**⁴ from the University of Naples⁵ "Federico II" with a master's thesis entitled *State of the art clustering techniques – Support Vector Methods and Minimum Bregman Information Principle.*⁶

Network specialist (GARR-B project)

27 May 2002 - 11 Dec 2002

Training course by GARR⁷ consortium: three months of theory and three more months of practice about the following topics: network protocols internals, structured wiring, security, routing and QoS, Unix/Linux and Windows sysadmin, LAN setup, Web basics and development.

Object Oriented Programming and Databases

01 May 2000 - 31 Jul 2000

OOP paradigm, client-server application development with Borland Delphi 6, CGI development with Borland Delphi 6, Database (Paradox) design and programming. Web development.

Skills and competences

Software engineering and Technical Leadership. Object Oriented Design and Design Patterns, Functional Design, Agent Oriented Design. Experience with both classical (Waterfall, Spiral, etc.) and modern (Agile, XP, Scrum, TDD, etc.) software development methodologies. Also experience with popular SCMs (SVN, CVS, Git), documentation generators (Doxygen, Javadoc, etc.). Experienced at tech-leading small teams (3 to 4 people). Strongly familiar with Continuous Integration and Multi-stage Deployment.

Advanced Web Engineering. 9+ years of experience. Always up to date on modern technologies (AJAX, Web services, RIAs, etc.) and open standards (HTML 5, CSS3, etc.);

Advanced (OO)-PHP development. 9+ years of experience in PHP/OOPHP development, both from scratch and on top of frameworks. Very good knowledge of well known PHP-based platforms and libraries: Drupal, WordPress, WordPress Mu, Pear. Other platforms: Yii, Symfony, CakePHP, Zend Framework, ez Components;

Advanced DBs. 9+ years of experience in designing and programming databases (MySQL, PostgreSQL). Extensive experience with SQL, PL/pgSQL, stored procedure, views, etc. Minor experience with Paradox, Oracle and PL/SQL;

Scalability and Performance of Web Applications. Experience with both back and front end performance issues. Experience with Web Applications in the <u>Cloud</u>, front-end caching via <u>Varnish</u>, back-end caching via <u>Memcached</u>, profiling via <u>XDebug</u> and <u>XHProf</u>, PHP performance enhancement via <u>APC</u>; many experiments with PHP compilers like <u>HipHop</u> or <u>PHC</u>;

¹ See http://eucip.com for more details.

² See http://www.environmentalprofessionals.eu.

³ For italian readers: Laurea quinquennale (in Informatica) secondo le modalità precedenti l'entrata in vigore del D.M. 509/99, equiparata alla Laurea magistrale ai sensi del D.M. 270/2004.

^{4 &}quot;With Honours"

⁵ See http://www.international.unina.it (english).

⁶ The thesis is available for download at http://thesis.neminis.org/2008/04/03/thesis-and-talk/.

⁷ See http://www.garr.it/garr-b-home-engl.shtml for more details.



Java developer. ~3 years of experience. Experience with <u>JSE</u>, <u>JEE</u> and exposure to many frameworks like <u>Spring</u>, <u>DWR</u>, <u>iBatis</u>, <u>GWT</u>. Experience also in *Agent Oriented Programming* with the <u>JADE</u> framework;

C++ developer. ~3 years of experience, focusing on scientific software development. Good knowledge of STL, Boost Libraries, LIBSVM, SVM-Light, etc.; minor experience with Shogun library.

Regular expressions. 5+ years of experience with both Perl regular expressions and POSIX ones;

Data mining, Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing. ~3 years of experience with data mining and machine learning algorithms, with special focus on unsupervised techniques ([co-]clustering, missing data values handling, collaborative filtering, etc.); experience with <u>Named Entity Retrieval</u> and <u>Opinion Mining</u>;

Human-computer interaction. Experience in optimising usability of applications, with special focus on web applications;

System administrator. 7+ years of experience with Linux system administration in medium size environments. Also managed *Mac OS X server* and *Windows server*. Extensive experience with <u>Bash shell programming</u>;

Minor skills. Delphi, Perl, Python, Apple Cocoa and Cocoa Touch (iPhone/iPod-Touch).

Languages⁸

Italian Mother tongue; **Neapolitan** Mother tongue;

English *Understanding*: proficient (C1), *Speaking*: proficient (C1), *Writing*: proficient (C1);

Spanish Understanding: basic (A2), Speaking: basic (A1), Writing: basic (A1).

Publications and Softwares

V. Russo, *State-of-the-art clustering techniques: Support Vector Methods and Minimum Bregman Information Principle*, Master's Thesis, Università degli studi di Napoli "Federico II", Corso Umberto I, 80100 Naples, Italy, February 2008.

V. Russo, *Clustering and classification in Information Retrieval: from standard techniques towards the state of the art*, Technical Report, Università degli studi di Napoli "Federico II", Corso Umberto I, 80100 Naples, Italy, September 2008.

- V. Russo, LIBSVM Plus, Software, http://neminis.org/software/libsvm-plus/
- V. Russo, Support Vector Clustering, Software, http://neminis.org/software/support-vector-clustering

References

Available upon request.

For italian readers only

Dati personali. Esprimo il consenso, ai sensi della legge 196/2003, per il trattamento dei dati personali;

Servizio di leva. Da non sostenere, ai sensi della legge 226/2004, causa slittamento in classe 1986;

Codice fiscale. RSS VCN 82B06 F839 F.

Oommon European Framework of Reference (CEF) levels (for more details see http://www.coe.int/T/DG4/Portfolio/?L=E&M=/main_pages/levels.html)